<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Ned Rossiter on Art@Net&amp;Software</title><link>https://art-net-software.gajdosik.org/tags/ned-rossiter/</link><description>Recent content in Ned Rossiter on Art@Net&amp;Software</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><copyright>Site by &lt;a href='https://gajdosik.org'>Andy Gajdosik&lt;/a></copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2024 10:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://art-net-software.gajdosik.org/tags/ned-rossiter/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Theory &amp; Internet Utopia</title><link>https://art-net-software.gajdosik.org/posts/internet-utopia/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://art-net-software.gajdosik.org/posts/internet-utopia/</guid><description>&lt;p>Criticism of the current conditions on the Internet as well as the daily experience of Internet reality can lead us to sadness, depression and a feeling of pure hopelessness.
It can block us from imagining alternatives, better ways of functioning of the Internet and online communities, and lead us to pure passivity or escapism.
But frustration can bear fruit and motivate action when it is combined with a positive vision of the future of the Internet.
For those of you who have not given up yet, or who want to find hope and desire for change, here are some tips for reading.&lt;/p></description><content>&lt;p>Criticism of the current conditions on the Internet as well as the daily experience of Internet reality can lead us to sadness, depression and a feeling of pure hopelessness.
It can block us from imagining alternatives, better ways of functioning of the Internet and online communities, and lead us to pure passivity or escapism.
But frustration can bear fruit and motivate action when it is combined with a positive vision of the future of the Internet.
For those of you who have not given up yet, or who want to find hope and desire for change, here are some tips for reading.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-internet-con-how-to-seize-the-means-of-computation---cory-doctorow-2024">The Internet Con: How to Seize the Means of Computation - Cory Doctorow (2024)&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Cory Doctorow’s The Internet Con: How to Seize the Means of Computation is a powerful manifesto for reclaiming the internet from the clutches of Big Tech.
In this concise yet compelling book, Doctorow exposes the manipulative strategies of tech giants that turn connection into commodification, locking users into &amp;ldquo;walled gardens&amp;rdquo; designed to extract maximum profit.
He argues for interoperability—the breaking down of barriers between platforms—as the key to dismantling these monopolistic systems.
With clear urgency and actionable insight, The Internet Con is not just a critique but a disassembly manual, empowering artists, technologists, and everyday users to reimagine a freer, more equitable digital landscape.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="internet-for-the-people-the-firght-for-out-digital-future---ben-tarnoff-2022">Internet for the People: The Firght for Out Digital Future - Ben Tarnoff (2022)&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Ben Tarnoff’s Internet for the People: The Fight for Our Digital Future is a call to action for reclaiming the internet from the grip of profit-driven privatization.
Tarnoff traces the internet&amp;rsquo;s transformation from a public resource into a tool of global capitalism, dominated by corporations like Google and Facebook.
His solution is bold yet clear: deprivatize the internet.
By shrinking the market&amp;rsquo;s influence and fostering publicly and cooperatively owned digital spaces, Tarnoff envisions an internet ruled by people, not profit.
This book is essential for those who believe in a democratic digital future, offering both a critique of the current system and a blueprint for revolutionary change.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="other-reads">Other reads&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://valiz.nl/publicaties/stuck-on-the-platform">Stuck on the Platform&lt;/a> - Geert Lovink (2022)
&lt;a href="https://networkcultures.org/blog/publication/organization-after-social-media/">Organization after Social Media&lt;/a> - Geert Lovink, Ned Rossiter (2018)&lt;/p></content></item></channel></rss>